

■ ek8093@rit.edu | 😭 emilykuang.github.io | 🖫 emilykuang | 🛅 emilykuang6

At the forefront of Human-Computer Interaction (HCI), Artificial Intelligence (AI), and User Experience (UX), my research focuses on designing and evaluating human-AI collaborative tools for improved usability and UX analysis. Honored with the 2023 Google PhD Fellowship in HCI, my work not only advances technology but also champions accessibility, focusing on inclusive computing education and assistive technology for diverse user groups.

## Education

### **Rochester Institute of Technology**

Rochester, NY, US

PHD IN COMPUTING AND INFORMATION SCIENCES

Aug 2020 - present

- Advised by Dr. Kristen Shinohara and Dr. Mingming Fan
- Participating in the AWARE-AI NSF Research Traineeship (NRT) Program

### **University of Waterloo**

Waterloo, ON, CA

Sept 2015 - Apr 2020

BASC IN BIOMEDICAL ENGINEERING

- · Capstone advised by Dr. John Zelek
- · Graduated on Dean's Honour List

# **Experience**

### **Rochester Institute of Technology**

Rochester, NY, US

GRADUATE RESEARCH ASSISTANT

Aug 2020 - present

- Conduct HCI research on the human-centered design of Al-powered technologies, focusing on visual analytic tools and conversational assistants to support usability analysis
- Design, conduct, and analyze research studies employing a variety of methods including interviews, surveys, design probes, usability studies, and quantitative experiments
- Author technical papers for publication and develop dissemination plans

### **Autodesk, HCI & Visualization Research Group**

Toronto, ON, CA

RESEARCH INTERN

May 2024 - present

• Working on projects at the intersection of generative AI and 3D design

**Meta, Reality Labs** Seattle, WA, US

**UX RESEARCH INTERN** 

*May 2023 - Aug 2023* 

- Designed and led a 20-participant interview study about using VR headsets, efficiently collaborating with research vendors
- Actively contributed to project brainstorming workshops and internal product demos
- Effectively communicated findings to diverse product stakeholders, promoting a comprehensive understanding of user perspectives and needs

**Meta, Reality Labs** Burlingame, CA, US

**UX RESEARCH INTERN** 

May 2022 - Aug 2022

- Conducted literature reviews and authored reports to inform the design of Ray-ban | Meta smartglasses
- Designed and conducted a user study with 30 participants to investigate audio performance
- Presented results to >100 product stakeholders including researchers, engineers, and cross-functional partners; recommendations led to changes in product design

Toronto, ON, CA

RESEARCH INTERN May 2021 - Aug 2021

- Worked on the DARPA Automating Scientific Knowledge Extraction (ASKE) program
- Designed wireframes and implemented new features in the human-machine interface (HMI) of a visual analytics system for multi-scale graph analysis and knowledge discovery

#### Huawei Technologies Canada, Human-Machine Interaction (HMI) Lab

Markham, ON, CA

RESEARCH ENGINEER

Jan - Aug 2019, May - Aug 2020

- Trained machine learning models for gesture recognition using Tensorflow
- Designed and conducted user experiments to explore novel interaction techniques on large screens using mid-air gesture input; contributed to the Huawei Developer Conference 2019

### University of Waterloo, Vision and Image Processing (VIP) Lab

Waterloo, ON, CA

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

May 2016 - Apr 2018

- Designed and 3D-printed a lens-free microscope and a smartphone spectrometer
- Conducted testing with biological specimens to achieve optical resolution in the nm range

## **Publications**

CONFERENCE PAPERS (PEER-REVIEWED)

# [C.13] Bridging the Literacy Gap for Adults: Understanding How Streamers Teach Adult Literacy on Livestreaming Platforms

SHIHAN FU, JIANHAO CHEN, EMILY KUANG, MINGMING FAN

Proceedings of the 2024 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems [Acceptance rate: 26.3%], 2024 DOI: 10.1145/3613904.3642423

# [C.12] Designing Unobtrusive Modulated Electrotactile Feedback on Fingertip Edge to Assist Blind and Low Vision (BLV) People in Comprehending Charts

Chutian Jiang, Yinan Fan, Junan Xie, Emily Kuang, Kaihao Zhang, Mingming Fan

Proceedings of the 2024 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems [Acceptance rate: 26.3%], 2024 DOI: 10.1145/3613904.3642546 (First two authors contributed equally) Best Paper Honorable Mention (Top 5%)

[C.11] Exploring the Opportunity of Augmented Reality (AR) in Supporting Older Adults Explore and Learn Smartphone Applications

XIAOFU JIN, WAI TONG, XIAOYING WEI, XIAN WANG, EMILY KUANG, XIAOYU MO, HUAMIN QU, MINGMING FAN

Proceedings of the 2024 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems [Acceptance rate: 26.3%], 2024

DOI: 10.1145/3613904.3641901

# [C.10] Mapping Accessibility Assignments into Core Computer Science Topics: An Empirical Study with Interviews and Surveys of Instructors and Students

EMILY KUANG, SELAH BELLSCHEIDT, DI PHAM, KRISTEN SHINOHARA, CATHERINE M. BAKER, YASMINE N. ELGLALY Proceedings of the 2024 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems [Acceptance rate: 26.3%], 2024 DOI: 10.1145/3613904.3642097

# [C.9] Enhancing UX Evaluation Through Collaboration with Conversational AI Assistants: Effects of Proactive Dialogue and Timing

EMILY KUANG, MINGHAO LI, MINGMING FAN, KRISTEN SHINOHARA

Proceedings of the 2024 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems [Acceptance rate: 26.3%], 2024 DOI: 10.1145/3613904.3642168

# [C.8] Exploring the Impact of Artificial Intelligence-Generated Content (AIGC) Tools on Social Dynamics in UX Collaboration

ZIYAN WANG, LUYAO SHEN, EMILY KUANG, SHUMENG ZHANG, MINGMING FAN

Proceedings of the 2024 ACM Conference on Designing Interactive Systems [Acceptance rate: 27.4%], 2024 (To appear)

# [C.7] Understanding Strategies and Challenges of Conducting Daily Data Analysis (DDA) Among Blind and Low-vision People

CHUTIAN JIANG, WENTAO LEI, EMILY KUANG, TENG HAN, MINGMING FAN

Proceedings of the 25th ACM SIGACCESS Conference on Computers and Accessibility [Acceptance rate: 30.2%], 2023 DOI: 10.1145/3597638.3608423

### [C.6] Enhancing Older Adults' Gesture Typing Experience Using the T9 Keyboard on Small Touchscreen Devices EMILY KUANG, RUIHUAN CHEN, MINGMING FAN

Proceedings of the 2023 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems [Acceptance rate: 27.6%], 2023 DOI: 10.1145/3544548.3581105

# [C.5] Collaboration with Conversational AI Assistants for UX Evaluation: Questions and How to Ask them (Voice

EMILY KUANG, EHSAN JAHANGIRZADEH SOURE, MINGMING FAN, JIAN ZHAO, KRISTEN SHINOHARA

Proceedings of the 2023 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems [Acceptance rate: 27.6%], 2023 DOI: 10.1145/3544548.3581247

### [C.4] Bridging the Generational Gap: Exploring How Virtual Reality Supports Remote Communication Between **Grandparents and Grandchildren**

XIAOYING WEI, YIZHENG GU, EMILY KUANG, XIAN WANG, BEIYAN CAO, XIAOFU JIN, MINGMING FAN Proceedings of the 2023 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems [Acceptance rate: 27.6%], 2023 DOI: 10.1145/3544548.3581405

### [C.3] "Merging Results Is No Easy Task": An International Survey Study of Collaborative Data Analysis Practices **Among UX Practitioners**

**EMILY KUANG, XIAOFU JIN, MINGMING FAN** 

Proceedings of the 2022 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems [Acceptance rate: 24.7%], 2022 DOI: 10.1145/3491102.3517647

### [C.2] "Too old to bank digitally?": A Survey of Banking Practices and Challenges Among Older Adults in China XIAOFU JIN, EMILY KUANG, MINGMING FAN

Proceedings of the 2021 ACM Designing Interactive Systems Conference [Acceptance rate: 27.7%], 2021 DOI: 10.1145/3461778.3462127

### [C.1] Compensated lens-free light field spectroscopy

AMENEH BOROOMAND, MOHAMMAD SHAFIEE, LINDA WAND, EMILY KUANG, FARNOUD KAZEMZADEH, ALEXANDER WONG International Conference on Inverse Problems in Engineering, 2017

### JOURNAL ARTICLES (PEER-REVIEWED)

### [J.3] CoUX: Collaborative Visual Analysis of Think-Aloud Usability Test Videos for Digital Interfaces

EHSAN JAHANGIRZADEH SOURE, EMILY KUANG, MINGMING FAN, JIAN ZHAO IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics 28.1 (2022) pp. 643–653. 2022 DOI: 10.1109/TVCG.2021.3114822 (First two authors contributed equally)

# [J.2] Compact, Field-Portable Lens-free Microscope using Superresolution Spatio-Spectral Light-field Fusion

FARNOUD KAZEMZADEH, EMILY KUANG, ALEXANDER WONG

Journal of Computational Vision and Imaging Systems 2.1 (2016). 2016 DOI: 10.15353/vsnl.v2i1.105

## $\lceil J.1 \rceil$ Enhanced Smartphone Spectroscopy via High-throughput Computational Slit

EMILY KUANG, FARNOUD KAZEMZADEH, ALEXANDER WONG

Journal of Computational Vision and Imaging Systems 2.1 (2016). 2016 DOI: 10.15353/vsnl.v2i1.97

## EXTENDED ABSTRACTS & WORKSHOP PAPERS (PEER-REVIEWED)

## [P.2] Crafting Human-AI Collaborative Analysis for User Experience Evaluation

**EMILY KUANG** 

In Extended Abstracts of the 2023 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems, 2023 DOI: 10.1145/3544549.3577042 (Accepted to the Doctoral Consortium)

### [P.1] A Multi-scale Visual Analytics Approach for Exploring Biomedical Knowledge

Fahd Husain, Rosa Romero-Gómez, Emily Kuang, Dario Segura, Adam Carolli, Lai Chung Liu, Manfred Cheung, Yohann Paris

Proceedings of the Workshop on Visual Analytics in Healthcare (VAHC), 2021

DOI: 10.1109/VAHC53616.2021.00010 Best Paper Award

## Honors and Awards \_\_\_\_\_

### RECEIVED DURING PHD

- 2024 **Best Paper Honorable Mention Award (Top 5%)**, CHI 2024
- 2024 Outstanding Graduate Student Award, RIT
- 2023 **Google Ph.D. Fellowship in Human-Computer Interaction**, Google
- 2022 AWARE-AI NRT Seed Funding Award, RIT
- 2022 Department Nomination for Microsoft Research Ph.D. Fellowship, RIT
- 2021 **Best Paper Award**, Workshop on Visual Analytics in Healthcare (VAHC)
- 2020 Merit-based Ph.D. Scholarship, RIT

#### RECEIVED DURING UNDERGRADUATE

2018 <b>Experience Award</b> , Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada
--

- 2018 **President's Research Award**, University of Waterloo
- 2017 **President's Research Award**, University of Waterloo
- 2016 Undergraduate Student Research Award, NSERC
- 2015 **President's Scholarship of Distinction**, University of Waterloo

## Invited Talks and Poster Presentations

Jun 2024	Invited speaker, Womxn in STEM Conference	Toronto, ON
Apr 2024	Presenter, RIT Graduate Showcase	Rochester, NY
Jan 2024	Invited panelist, AWARE-AI NRT Retreat: Session on Resume Building & Internships	Remote
Nov 2023	Invited speaker, Youth Professional Career Development Series	Remote
Apr 2023	Poster presenter, CHI Doctoral Consortium	Hamburg, Germany
Oct 2022	Poster presenter, RIT Artificial Intelligence Summit	Rochester, NY
Apr 2022	Poster presenter, CRA-WP Grad Cohort for Women	New Orleans, LA

# Teaching Experience \_\_\_\_\_

### **ISTE-798 Future Interactions**

RIT

TEACHING ASSISTANT

Jan 2024 - May 2024

- Collaborate with the course instructor to plan and organize course materials
- · Mentor students and provide constructive feedback on assignments, projects, and research

#### **GUEST LECTURES**

Sept 2023	Human-AI Collaboration for UX Evaluation, PhD Research Colloquium (CISC896)	RIT
Apr 2023	Older Adults' Gesture Typing Experience, Design For Accessibility (ISTE266)	RIT
Nov 2021	Visual Analysis of Think-Aloud Usability Test Videos, Visual Analytics (ISTE782)	RIT

LAST UPDATED: JUNE 2024 4

### Service

### SERVICE TO THE PROFESSION

2024	Reviewer: Technical Papers, UIST 2024	Special Recognition		
2024	Reviewer: Technical Papers, VIS 2024			
2023	Associate Chair, Chinese CHI 2023			
2023	Reviewer: Technical Papers, CHI 2024	Special Recognition		
2023	Reviewer: Technical Papers, CSCW 2023			
2023	Reviewer: Technical Papers, Frontiers in Computer Science			
2022	Reviewer: Technical Papers, CHI 2023	Special Recognition		
2022	Student Volunteer (In-person), CHI 2022			
2021	Reviewer: Technical Papers, CHI 2022			
2021	Student Volunteer (Virtual), VIS 2021			
2021	Reviewer: Late Breaking Work, Chinese CHI 2021			
Service to the University				
2023	PhD Student Representative, Board of Trustees Meeting			
2023	PhD Student Representative, GRAD Open House			
2023	<b>Trainee Council Representative</b> , AWARE-AI NSF Research Traineeship (2022-2023)			

# Additional Professional Experience \_\_\_\_\_

Project Judge, Genius Olympiad

### North Inc. (now acquired by Google)

COMPUTER VISION DEVELOPER

Kitchener, ON, CA

Apr 2018 - Aug 2018

• Designed algorithm to quantify image sharpness for multi-camera system assembly

### Synaptive Medical Inc.

2022

OPTICS ENGINEERING INTERN

Sept 2017- Dec 2017

• Investigated the stabilization of stereoscopic videos for a neurosurgical robot

#### St. Michael's Hospital

Toronto, ON, CA

Toronto, ON, CA

MEDICAL IMAGING RESEARCH ASSISTANT

Jan 2017 - Apr 2017

• Worked on a video processing pipeline for non-invasive detection of diabetic foot ulcers

# Media Coverage \_\_\_\_\_

10/16/2023 Two RIT students earn Google Ph.D. Fellowships for AI computing research,	RIT News
10/13/2023 Google PhD Fellowship recipients,	Google Research
09/30/2023 AWARE-AI NSF Research Traineeship Program Newsletter (Trainee Spotlight),	AWARE-AI NRT